<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the preparation to the holy supper of our onely saueour and redeemer, Iesus Christe Necessarie for all them that vvil vworthely approche to the Lordes holy table. Also a dialogue containing the principall points, which they that wil recieue the Supper ought to knowe and vnderstand. By Yues Rouspeau minister of the vvord of God. Ttanslated [sic] out of French into English by R.B.</title>
            <title>Traitté de la preparation à la saincte cene. English.</title>
            <author>Rouspeau, Yves.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21351.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106673</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842386</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842386</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7035</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7035)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 668:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the preparation to the holy supper of our onely saueour and redeemer, Iesus Christe Necessarie for all them that vvil vworthely approche to the Lordes holy table. Also a dialogue containing the principall points, which they that wil recieue the Supper ought to knowe and vnderstand. By Yues Rouspeau minister of the vvord of God. Ttanslated [sic] out of French into English by R.B.</title>
                  <title>Traitté de la preparation à la saincte cene. English.</title>
                  <author>Rouspeau, Yves.</author>
                  <author>R. B., fl. 1570.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [Iohn Allde for] Lucas Harison,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1570?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Rouspeau, Yves. Traitté de la preparation à la saincte cene.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A preparation to the Lords supper.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7035:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7035:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A TREATISE of the preparation to the holy Supper of our onely Saue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Redéemer, Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Neceſſary for all them that vvil vvorthely approche to the Lords holy Table.</p>
            <p>Alſo a dialogue containing the principall points, whiche they that wil receiue the Supper ought to knowe and vnderſtand.</p>
            <p>By Yues Rouſpeau miniſter of the vvord of God. Ttanſlated out French into English by R.B.</p>
            <q>¶ Let a man examine him ſelf, and ſo let him eat of this Bread and drink of this Cup.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at London by Lucas Hariſon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7035:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7035:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right worshipful S. Iohn</hi> Zouch of Codner Knight R.B wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a bleſſed life, happy dayes with great increace of vvorship.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the ſundry woorks of many ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, learned &amp; wiſe men (right vvorshipful) I fide no one thing more generally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended then the trauel that procureth profit &amp; vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to the common welth: for to this end al the eſtate of mans life te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, that vvhilſt vve co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in this baſe territory heer, our vvhole indeuour should be imploied to the ben fit of our cuntrey in ſome reſpect. And for this cauſe the moſte renovvned Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and famouſe Princes of the vvorld in times paſt had alvvaies diligent care to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce ſuch as by their pollicy conſerued their kingdomes in publique tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quilitie, or by their valiantnes vanquished their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, or by iuſtice ſuppreſſed the vvicked either els by their vvritings &amp; learned docu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments inſtructed the Vulgaritie to vertuous liuing. Anaxarchus amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the Phenicians alovved beſt of the maintainers of ciuil con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cord, Numa Pompilius exhorteth the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ro recompence thoſe largly that retur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned victorious from any battail, Promotne
<pb facs="tcp:7035:3"/>us willed the Egiptians to make great accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thoſe that were true Iuſticiaries. And Bias king of the Argiues, commaunded his people aboue all others, to honour &amp; reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence moſte their vvriters and teachers of vviſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. Octauian and Mecenas gratified virgil the lerned poet, with ſuch rich preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that Seruius who vvriteth of him, affirmeth that in short ſpace hee was valued tobe worth ſix M. Seſterns, vvhich amounteth to tvvo hundred M. crovvnes, ſuch zeale vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vertue reigned in the noble Peares of that age, that they accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted thoſe gifts beſt beſtovved which vvere imploied vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them that vvere ſinguler in any facultie, to then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that others in hope of preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, might the rather be incouraged to immitate their ſteps. If that lack of liberalitie be found in the princes of this parfet time, in remune. rating the vertues vvhich abounded ſo plen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifully in the nobilitie of thoſe obſcure day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es vvherin nature (vvithout the knowledge of the eternall) bare the onely ſvvay, hovv much it is to be lamented I refer to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of thoſe that by reading may diſcerne the praiſes belonging iuſtly vnto the one, and by preſent ſight may beholde the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults of the other</p>
            <p>If a greater deſire to pleaſure their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb facs="tcp:7035:3"/>vvas found in that people which vvere gouerned only by the inſtinct of nature, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is in thoſe vvhich novv may be direct<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed by that pure &amp; moſt bleſſed operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſpirit of God: vvhat punishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is due to their recheleſſe neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce let thoſe that read the ſacred Scriptures diſcide, vvhere it is moſte apparant to be ſeen, vvith vvhat vigor God punished the vnprofitable ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, hovv he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that euery tre vvhich brought not forth good frute, shuld be hevve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dovvn and caſt into the fire. Theſe threatnings (if nothing els vvould moue) should ſtir vp e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man to make ſome increce of thoſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents vvhich God hath lent him, rather then through ſlouthfulnes to bury them in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie vvithout reaping gaines to them ſelues, or yeelding a iuſt account to God, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefit to their countrey, trevv allegeance to their prince, furtherance to their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or pleaſure to their freends to vvhome they be bound. To auoid theſe inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniences &amp; to eſchevv the infamy that breedeth through idelnes: I thought it good to imploy my dili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gence in tranſlating this ſmall Treatiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring rather to bee accounted a profitable Bee: then to be ſuſpected for a hurtfull Drone, for though the Volume be not large, nor my laboure great: yet poſſible,
<pb facs="tcp:7035:4"/>there is as great conſolation to be found for the repentant ſinner as in bigger Tomes.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I vvould ſignifie vnto your vvorship, the good vvil I beare you and the deſire I haue to acquit ſome parte of thoſe curieſies vvhiche I haue receiued at your hands, I haue preſumed to craue your patro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nage, to this the firſt frutes of my labour, ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping that you vvil vouchſafe the accepta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thereof in ſuche parte as vvith good vvill I offer it. And though that it ſcape not free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſures of ſome vvhoſe delight is to carp at euery light occaſion, yet if it may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your fauourable liking, my deſire is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied, and ſo (vvith remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of my du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie) I take my leue, wishing helth to your per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vvorship to your parentage, and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perousſucceſſe in all your indeuours.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your vvorships to commaund. R.B</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>¶ <hi>Yues Rouſpeau to the Chriſtian Reader,</hi> helth from Ieſus Chriſte our Lord.</head>
            <p>AMongſt the cauſes of common calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſcourges wherwith God puni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſheth the world, <hi>S. Paule</hi> maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the abuſe and contempt of the Lords Supper: ſayi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, for this cauſe many are weke and ſick among you, and many ſléep. For if we would iudge our ſelues, we ſhould not bée
<pb facs="tcp:7035:4"/>iudged. Therfore we ought not to meruail that the laſt yéer God did ſo ſeuerely puniſh this poor Realme of <hi>France,</hi> with plague, war and famin. For the contempt of the Goſpel, and the abuſe and prophanation of the Lords holy Supper, were the cauſe therof: ſo that niether they that folowed the Popes faction ought to complain of God, nor they likewiſe that make profeſſion of the Goſpel, becauſe there was a fault bothe in the one &amp; the other. Firſt touching the abuſes of the Papiſts, we are able to ſet down ſure iudgement by the woord of God how that the Maſſe is wholly fraught with blaſphemyes: how it aboliſheth the holy Supper of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte: how the remembrance of his death and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is therin ſuppreſſed &amp; brought to nought, how there is no communion, and that in ſted that Ieſus Chriſte commaunded all his in ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall to take, eat, and drink the bred &amp; wine, one only taketh, eateth &amp; driketh for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt. We ſee there moreouer, how they cauſe a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature tobe worſhiped therin, yea a morſell of bread in ſtede of the Creatour, how they ſéek Chriſte Ieſus there in earth, wher as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, the Apoſtles créed, &amp; the olde Canons teach vs to haue our harts lift vp on high and to ſéek him by faith in Heauen. To be ſhort there are to be ſéen many other deteſtable and
<pb facs="tcp:7035:5"/>infinit abuſes whiche I now paſſe ouer with ſilence. Now then ſéeing they haue obſtinatly planted &amp; grounded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in that affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea &amp; for the maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſo vile and wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked a thing haue put to death ſo many good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo many holy &amp; true martirs of our Lord, Ieſꝰ Chriſte. Hath not God rightfully viſited vs in this behalf? Secondly we ſée alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ther were great &amp; notable abuſes on their behalfe, that made profeſſion of the true woord of God. How many were there which knew no more then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſts to giue any reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their faith and which preſented them ſelues like beaſts to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords holy Supper? Some came thither as ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſes, other as ſwine leding a diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute &amp; ſlanderous life. I wil not ſpeak of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit number of hipocrits, falſe brethern, trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters &amp; Apoſtates,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.48.</note> which were vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; had a countenance &amp; ſhew of honeſtie. Therfore is was not without cauſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath of god was kindled againſt his people, &amp; that they were ſcourged with ſtripes, for wittigly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the knowledge of his holy name. Now that this good God through his Sonne Ieſus Chriſte, may caſt his pitiful and merciful eye vpon this ſo poore and deſolate Realme: it be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>houeth bothe the one and the other to learne hence forwarde to ſerue and honor God accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to his woord, better then they haue doon,
<pb facs="tcp:7035:5"/>eſpetially that they take héede that héerafter they prophane not by any meanes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Ieſus Chriſte our Lord. To this ende and purpoſe they may read this little tretiſe, wherin they ſhall finde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the true preparing of our ſelues to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords ſupper, conſiſteth not in decking of the body, fair garments, pomps,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.24.</note> countenaunces, and outward profeſſion of the name of God, but in cleneneſſe of hart, and vp rightnes of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to th' end that God who is a ſpirit, may be alſo ſerued of his in Spirit and trueth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>¶ To come worthely to the holy Supper of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte / <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</note> we muſt examine our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues according too the admonition of the Apoſtle Saint Paule. Now the examination of our ſelues conſiſteth cheefely in foure poynts / that is to ſay / in Faith / repentance / giuing of thanks to God / and looue towards our neighbours.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>Of Faith. The firſt Article.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt of all we muſt haue faith that is to ſay, a certain &amp; infallible aſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rance &amp; firme perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that God is a merciful father<note n="1" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 35.5: 6.7. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16.</note> vnto vs in the name of his ſonne Ieſꝰ Chriſte our Lord, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e he deliuered to death for vs. This faith co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not of vs,<note n="2" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Ro.</hi> 7.18. 1. <hi>cor.</hi> 2.14.</note> nether is it grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon vs, nether vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is in vs, but
<pb facs="tcp:7035:6"/>it commeth from God and is grounded<note n="3" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math,</hi> 11.25.26.27. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.26</note> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, and vpon the promiſes of the goſpel confirmed inwardly within vs, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> working of the holy Ghoſt, whiche cryeth in our harts <hi>Abba.</hi>
                  <note n="(4)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 8 15 <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6.</note> that is to ſay father. Furthermore this faith is nouriſhed, confirmed and increa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed in vs by the holy Sacraments. For in the Supper: God as a good father (after that hee hath once brought vs into his Church by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme) nouriſheth vs ſpiritually with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſubſtance of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſte, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying and making proper vnto euery one of vs, the merit of his death &amp; paſſion. To this end and purpoſe is it that Ieſus Chriſte him ſelf giueth vs the bread and Wine:<note n="5" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Mat</hi> 14.21. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.19 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14.</note> that he commaundeth vs, to eat and drink it: that he ſaith that the Bread is his body whiche is giuen for vs, and that the Wine is his Blood which is ſhed for the remiſſion of our ſinnes: by whiche woordes he giueth him ſelf wholly vnto vs, he wilbe our nouriſhment and ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life: hée will dwell in vs by his holy Spirit, and wil that we abide in him by faith, that through beléef we may not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,<note n="6" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.36.28.</note> but haue eternall life, wherof he is the onely heyre and giuer.<note n="7" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 8.7. <hi>Math.</hi> 11 <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17, 12 27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28.18.</note> In like ſorte the breaking of the Bread of the Supper ſerueth to the confirmation of our faith and ſure war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ranting of our ſaluation, in ſo much as it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth
<pb facs="tcp:7035:6"/>vs and cauſeth vs to ſee with ſpirituall eyes, that Ieſus Chriſte was once broken with the paines of death in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from the ſame, and to get vs eternall life. Alſo, in that that by the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſte Ieſus, we take the Bread in our hands, and then the Cup, more ouer in that that we eate the Bread and drink the Wine, whiche turn into the nouriſhment of our bodyes: we are certyfied, that by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Faith we take and embrace Ieſus Chriſte our Lord for our onely Saueour and redéem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that by the ſame Faith we eat his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſpiritually, and drink his blood to the hope of eternall life.</p>
               <p>Now euery one of vs muſt liue by his owne faith,<note n="8" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aba.</hi> 2 4. <hi>Ro.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38</note> according as we may make our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion in the beleef whiche is called the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, in that that euery man ſaith by him ſelf I beleelue in God, and ſaith not we beleeue.</p>
               <p>We muſt not heer caſt our braines or think vpon the beléeuing or vnbeleeuing, vpon the worthynes or vnworthynes of an other man but vpon our owne. For <hi>Saint Paule</hi> dooth not teach vs to examin other men, or that other men ſhould examine vs, but he ſaith namely, let a man examine him ſelf.<note n="9" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor</hi> 11.28.</note> Therfore let euery one of vs for his owne parte be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his hert, that Ieſus Chriſte the trewe
<pb facs="tcp:7035:7"/>Meſſias is come into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to ſaue ſinners<note n="10" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.13. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Luc.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.35.</note> amongſt whome he ought to account and eſtéeme him ſelf (by the example of <hi>s. Paule</hi>) the chéefeſt.<note n="11" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15</note> Let him beléeue that Ieſus Chriſte came down from Heauen into Earth<note n="12" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.13.</note> to lift him vp from Earth to Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he was made the Sonne of man:<note n="13" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Ro.</hi> 1.3.</note> to make him the Childe of God, that he was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt<note n="14" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.20 <hi>Luc.</hi> 1 31.</note> and that he was borne of the Virgin mary:<note n="15" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 7 14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.25 <hi>Luc</hi> 1.31.</note> to purifie and clenſe his wicked conception &amp; birth. Let him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him ſelf that the Sonne of God hath ouercome the Deuil:<note n="16" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Luc</hi> 4 1.</note> to deliuer him from the tiranny and ſlauiſh ſubiection of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, that he hath fulfilled all the Law<note n="17" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Luc.</hi> 16 27 <hi>Ro.</hi> 10.4.</note> (loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God his father with all his hart, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and might and his neighbour as him ſelf) to get him iuſtice, that he appéered before Pilat<note n="18" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 27.11 <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.2 <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.3. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.33.</note> an earthly Iudge, and receiued as euil doo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er ſentence of condemnation for this life: to exempt him from appering before the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iudgement ſeat of Gods iuſtice to receiue ſentence of death &amp; euer laſting damnation, for that he had offended one eternall and euer laſting God. Let him aſſure him ſelf that the ſame Ieſu Chriſte went down to hel<note n="19" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 22.1 <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.46. <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.14.</note> for him, that is to ſay that he ſuffred the ſorrows and terrours of the ſecond death, and of the ſincere wrath of God to deliuer him, that he
<pb facs="tcp:7035:7"/>dyed a death accurſed of God<note n="20" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi> 21.23. <hi>Gala.</hi> 3.13.</note> in that hée was hanged on the Croſſe: to purchaſe him life &amp; bleſſing before God, that he roſe again, for a gage<note n="21" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.6. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Ioh</hi> 20.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.24.</note> and aſſurance of his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he aſſended into Heauen,<note n="22" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.58 <hi>Act.</hi> 2.9.</note> for a certain token that he alſo ſhal aſſend thither, that he ſitteth on the right hand of God his Father: to bée for him an euerlaſting Préeſt teacher, king defender, reconciler, and aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, tobe ſhort, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he ſhall come at his laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, for his comfort &amp; ful redemption. We muſt alſo euery one of vs for his owne parte make proper vnto our ſelues, yea and make ours all the goodnes &amp; all the riches that is in Ieſus Chriſte: becauſe that in giuing him ſelf to vs he giueth vs alſo his benefits. So then in that that Ieſus Chriſte is God: it is to make vs partakers of his diuinitie, in that that hée is heyre and Lord of the world: it is to make vs partakers of his Lordſhippe and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, &amp; that we recouer in him the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all things, which we loſt in Adam, in that hée is well belooued of his Father: it is that we may bee acceptable vnto him, in that that hée is riche: it is to make vs Partakers of his riches, in that that hée hath all power againſt the Deuil, Sin, Hel, Antichriſte the worlde, and all our enemies: it is to defend and ſheelde vs, in that that
<pb facs="tcp:7035:8"/>he is iuſt and good, it is to iuſtifye vs, &amp; make vs good, in that that he is happy and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, it is to make vs partakers of his bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and immortalitie.</p>
               <p>When we ſhall thus particulerly applye all the actions and benefits of Ieſus our Lord and alſo all his eſſentiall qualityes vnto our ſelues, putting a whole truſt in him, and in his promiſes, and diſtruſting our ſelues, then may we boldly come to the Lords table, wher at we ſhall inioy Ieſus Chriſte God and man by the benefit of faith, and ſhall feel moreouer a great increace &amp; augmentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame.</p>
               <p>But we muſt note that it is impoſſible for vs to be vnite and made one with Chriſte, and to be made partakers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treaſures and riches which are in him, vnleſſe we firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Antichriſte and his kingdome, and vnleſſe we deteſt all Idolatry, ſuperſtion and traditions of men, directly contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure ſeruice of God, bounded &amp; limitted out in his woord. For ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God is our onely creator: and he giueth him ſelf<note n="23" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12.</note> wholly vnto vs in the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſꝰ Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Iſaack in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e all the nations of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth are bleſſed<note n="24" place="margin">
                     <hi>Een.</hi> 12.18.</note> it is great reaſon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> likewiſe by faith we giue vp our ſelues &amp; yéeld vs wholly vnto god. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God in his law dooth right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully require of his people, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they haue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:7035:8"/>Gods but him.<note n="25" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ec.</hi> 20.2.</note> And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they loone him withall their hart, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all their ſoule, with all their ſtrength &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, that is to ſay, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al their partes aſwel inward as outward. And thence is it alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God dooth not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke &amp; reproue all them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> halt on both ſides.<note n="26" place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18.20.</note> but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they whiche ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vnto ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Gods, ſhould be put to death.<note n="27" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.5.</note> And to this purpoſe <hi>S. Paule</hi> (minding to warn the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to flée from Idolatrye) vſeth an argument taken from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knitting to gither &amp; vnion that we haue with Ieſꝰ Chriſt our lord in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper ſpeaking after this ſort.<note n="28" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</note> The cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the blood of Chriſte? And the bread which we breke is it not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the body of Chriſte? As if hée would ſay that ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Corinthians</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e not to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper to be partakers ſimply of earthly elements but to be partakers really &amp; in déed of the body &amp; blood of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to be made one with him by faith, and be made fleſh of his fleſh &amp; bones of his bones, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were to great wickednes and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to be preſent in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſemblyes of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels or to be partaker of their Idolatry, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle addeth afterward<note n="29" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21.</note> that the <hi>Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not drik of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cup of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> L. &amp; the cup of Deuils: &amp; that they cannot be partakers of
<pb facs="tcp:7035:9"/>the Lords Table and of the table of Deuils. Wherby he ſignifieth that it is impoſſible to ſerue God and the deuil togither, &amp; that who ſo euer dooth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with Idolatry: dooth manifeſtly renounce our Lord Ieſus Chriſte. Therfore ſéeing that darknes is no more con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to light, vice to vertue, death to life, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice to Hel, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope and his doctrine is contrary to our Lord Ieſus Chriſte and to his holy goſpel: it behooueth all trew faithful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to withdraw them ſelues wholly from po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and caſt of without delay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yoke of that Romiſh Antichriſt, that they may giue them ſelues wholly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice of this ſaueour &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer Ieſus Chriſte, but if ſo be that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion that we haue with the ſonne of God, and the promiſes of the heauenly Father can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not intice and perſwade vs to yéeld our ſelues wholly to God, to put our truſt in him only, to ſerue and worſhip him only, according to his wil, but that we wil yet cleue vnto Antichriſt and his ſeruants &amp; miniſters: yet at the leſt, let the threatnings and iudgements of God hinder vs and fear vs ſo to doo, as when it is ſaid<note n="30" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo.</hi> 18.4.</note> go out of her my people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye be not par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>takers in her ſinnes, and that ye receiue not of her plagues. And again,<note n="31" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo.</hi> 14.9.10.11.</note> if any man wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip the beaſt and his Image and receiue his mark in his forehed, or in his hand the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:7035:9"/>ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, yea of the pure wine, which is poured into the cup of his wrath, and he ſhalbe tormented in fire &amp; brimſtone before the holy Aungels, and before the Lamb. And that ſtink of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall aſcend euermore: and they ſhall haue no reſt day nor night, whiche worſhip the beaſt and his Image, and who ſo euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth the print of his name. And again.<note n="32" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo.</hi> 21.8.</note> The fearful and vnbeléeuing, the abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble murtherers, whoremongers, Sorcerers, Idolatours, and all lyers ſhal haue their parte in the lake which burneth with fire &amp; brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone which is the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d death. Let this ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be wel printed in our harts, that we be not ſeduced and deſtroyed with the vain ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of this world, which think it a thing not impoſſible to ſerue God and the deuil, Ieſus Chriſte and Antichriſte, to folow the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of God, and of men, and to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie the affections of the ſpirit and of the fleſh all at once.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>¶ Of Repentance. Article. 2.</head>
               <p>THe preparation wherof we ſpake before touching Faith which applied vnto euery one of vs particulerly, Ieſus Chriſte with all his riches and bleſſings can haue no place in vs, vnleſſe it bring foorth alſo in vs a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: that is to ſay, a true miſliking of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil,
<pb facs="tcp:7035:10"/>and a burning loue &amp; affection of goodneſſe, as we ſee the example in <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note n="1" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 51.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Peeter</hi>
                  <note n="2" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 26.75. <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.72. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.61.</note> 
                  <hi>Paule,</hi>
                  <note n="3" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 9.5. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1 13</note> and other holy men. We muſt haue a ſorowe and vnfained greef, for that we haue offended God, for that we haue before times wickedly abuſed our creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, redemption, and Baptiſme, for that we haue prouoked God with all our me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, for that we haue abuſed our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, hart, tung, feet and hands: for that we haue giuen and ſet foorth our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and bodyes (which are the temples wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God would dwel) to Infidelitie, Idolatrye, ſuperſtition, filthines, blaſphemy, whordo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, extortion, vſury, robery, gluttony, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ambition, exceſſe, ryot &amp; other worldly vanities which is aſmuch as if we wold haue lodged God the father, the ſonne and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt: in a moſte ſtinking and filthy priuy. We muſt therfore be ſory for our wicked life paſſed, vſing a true and ſeuere examining of our ſelues, which may bring forth in vs a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſantneſſe and horrour of our fore paſſed renting and breaking by all maner of menes of the law of God, to folow the wil of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, of the world and of the fleſh. Now the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king<note n="4" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14 21. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 2 42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.7. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14.</note> of the bread of the Supper (which is omitted in the paoſure of the Papiſtꝭ) ſhould cauſe vs to acknowledge and deteſt our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, that is to ſay, whatſoeuer is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in
<pb facs="tcp:7035:10"/>vs contrary &amp; repugnaunt to the pure and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly law of God. For in that that the bread is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for vs, or rather in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that we breke the bread of the Supper our of Lord Ieſꝰ Chriſte: it ſignifieth vnto vs that indéed it is we, that it is our ſinnes and iniquityes, which haue crucified &amp; put to death the Lord of life, who is the very ſame Ieſus Chriſte our Lord. So that we muſt not doo as in times paſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels did, which made great lamentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and inuectiues againſt the Iewes, <hi>Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, Herod, Iudas,</hi> and them that had execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and put Chriſt to death, and in the mene ſeaſon flattered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues: vaunting of their owne merits and deſerts, and did not narow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider that <hi>Iudas, Pontious Pilate,</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> were but executers and miniſters of their impietyes and ſinnes. Let vs therefore conſider in the breaking of the bread, that our ſinnes, yea the ſinnes of euery one of vs ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, crucified the ſonne of God, &amp; brake him with the ſorowes of the firſt and ſecond death, as namely the woords of the Supper doo ſhew that the body of Ieſus Chriſt was broken for vs, &amp; his blood was ſhed for the remiſſion of our ſinnes. And our heauenly father witne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeth the ſame, ſpeaking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of his ſonne<note n="5" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 53.3</note> for the ſinnes of my people, haue I ſmitten him. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if it be ſo that our ſinnes beeing way
<pb facs="tcp:7035:11"/>in the balaunce of the Iuſtice of God, were found to be ſo weightie and of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce that his wrath could neuer haue béen appeaſed towards vs, but by the death of his onely Sonne, which maketh ful ſatiſfaction, I ſay, by the cruel and ignominious death of the croſſe. How ſhould not we hence forwarde deteſt &amp; abhorre our ſin, as that which is the cruel &amp; bloody murtherer of the onely ſonne of God? Beholde the<note n="6" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.4.51.</note> Sun &amp; the Moon, behold the element, beholde the vale of the Temple, beholde the ſtones &amp; Rocks which were moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at the death of Ieſus Chriſte, which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed foorth tokens of ſorow, and we which bere within our ſelues the cauſe of his death, ſhall not we haue in horrour and deteſtation this curſed enemy ſin, that is lodged within vs?</p>
               <p>Shall we ſuffer him to rule &amp; dwell in vs, as before, that it may bring home death vnto vs? Not ſo: but we muſt deteſt it as that that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time ſeperated vs from God our chéefeſt happineſſe, as that that cauſed vs to looſe the Image and ſimilitude of God, according to which we were created at the beginning by God. It is that that hath wholly deſtroyed vs, that hath depriued vs of holineſſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, that hath baniſhed vs out of paradiſe, that hath made vs flaues to the tiranny of the deuil, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath made vs ſubiect to ſo many miſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryes,
<pb facs="tcp:7035:11"/>and diſeaſes, and tobe ſhort, bothe to the firſt and ſecond death, it is that which after it had ſet a bar &amp; deuiſion betwéen God and vs, cauſed vs to ſée our owne filthines, purchaſed vnto vs ſhameful &amp; vilanous infamy, made vs to tremble at the voice of our God which was before moſte pleaſant &amp; loouing vnto vs. It is that wherby the wrath of God is heaped vpon men, that maketh the Earth to become barrain and to bring foorth thornes and thiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, that cauſeth women to bring foorth in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and that men eat their bread in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweat and labour of their bodyes. Séeing then that ſin bringeth foorth and procureth vnto vs day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſo many miſeries: it foloweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we ought to withdraw our ſelues from it, if we wil not be wilful enemies of our owne happines &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation. Now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I cite héer all diſordered and flaunderous perſons, which notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding are ſo impudent to preſent them ſelues to the Lords holy table. I aſke them what it is that they promiſed to God and his church in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme? They wil anſwer me that they promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed. God to renounce the Deuil and all his works. But one of the chéef and principall works of the deuil is ſin. Why doo they not then abſtain from it? Why are they tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours &amp; diſobedient to God and his Church? Why haue they conſpired with the deuil, the
<pb facs="tcp:7035:12"/>world and the fleſh, againſt their owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? How dare they preſent them ſelues bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, to aſke him pardon and remiſſion of their ſinnes: ſéeing that more and more, they hepe ſin vpon ſin, and crucifie &amp; kil again (as much as in them lyeth) the ſonne of God, or at the leaſt make a ſcorne &amp; ſcoffe of the purging of his blood which was applyed vnto them in Baptiſme? Put the caſe that a wicked man, poor and deſtitute of all help, were fallen into a mire whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce out he could by no menes raiſe vp him ſelf, and that ſome yung Prince paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that way, took y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paines to draw him out of this ditch to make him clene, to clad him with gorgeous and pretious apparel, if this wicked man, &amp; poor miſerable caitif fall again into this mire &amp; beray bothe him ſelf and his apparel, béeing moreouer in great daunger of his life, would not one think that this man were maruelouſly vnkinde and a contemner of that princely bounty and goodneſſe, and on the other ſide, a wilful &amp; ſworne enemy of his owne helth, worthy tobe loſt &amp; caſt away with out any help or aſſiſtance? Euen ſo ſoundeth our cauſe with Ieſus Chriſte. We fel all into the pudle of ſin in the perſon of Adam<note n="7" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 15.</note> we are all wicked dooers and worthy of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth thouſand gibbetꝭ before God, we can by no meanes get out of our ſelues and out of the
<pb facs="tcp:7035:12"/>ditch of deſtruction wherinto we are al fallen of our owne fault. Beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne of God, the king of kings, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord of Lords, which com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth to draw vs out of this pudle, which com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth to waſh vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his pretious blood, whiche vouchſafeth to clad vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the proper Cloke of his righteouſnes &amp; innocency. If we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e again to wallow our ſelnes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puddle of ſin, if we pleſe our ſelues in it, if we defile &amp; be durt the robe of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy which he hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme, are we not manifeſt contemners of the ineſtimable looue &amp; gift of Ieſus Chriſte, &amp; are moreouer worthy to rot a thouſand times in our filthynes, or rather to gnaſh our téeh euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuilꝭ in hel? It is euident.</p>
               <p>Séeing then that it is ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the end of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, baptiſme, &amp; iuſtification requireth of vs to abſtain from ſin, (ſo farfoorth as po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſibly we may, and our fleſhly infirmitie wil ſuffer) we muſt take all paines &amp; diligence by the vertue of the ſpirit of God to caſt out from vs all foulenes and filthynes, Idolatry, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, rebellion, hatred, murder, whordome, theft and vſury and all other things contrary to the holy law, if we wil not be more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate towards Ieſus Chriſte and open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his Church and our owne ſaluation. But becauſe it is not ſufficient for the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a true &amp; helthful repentance to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:7035:13"/>our miſery, to abhorre it, to confeſſe it &amp; to abſtain fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, but we muſt alſo knowe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and doo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good whiche God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth in his woord: we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which ought erneſtly to ſtir vs vp to the ſanctifying of the name of God. Firſt in that we are ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and made one with Chriſte Ieſus in the Supper in that we are made fleſh of his fleſh, and bones of his bones, in that we liue by his holy ſpirit. Ought not this vpon good cauſe to exhort vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forme our ſelues to the Image and likenes of the holineſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte? Can he dwel in vs, nouriſh vs with his owne ſubſtance, quicken vs with his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit, ioyne vs vnto him ſelf by the bond of faith, yet ſo that he his holy ſpirit &amp; faith bring not foorth in vs good and holy woorks? Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, for ſo much as he dooth not giue him ſelfe vnto vs halfmele &amp; deſtitute of his qualities, and richis, and accompanied with all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all gifts &amp; bleſſings, adorned with righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; perfection, accompanied with innocency and ſanctification, how can we receiue Ieſus Chriſte inriched with all his graces that the righteouſnes of our hed may not ſhine in vs which are his members, yea, ſhine in all our partes aſwel in warde as outward? Muſt it néeds be that the two parts of our ſoule that is to ſay, our minde and hart, which ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend
<pb facs="tcp:7035:13"/>&amp; take holde of the promiſes of God, which ought to receiue by faith the body and blood of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, that is to ſay, whole Ieſus Chriſte true God, equall in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſpect to God his father, &amp; true man made of humain body and ſoule: that this minde and hart I ſay muſt be applied to the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; looue of worldly and wicked things, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtitute of the knowledge &amp; looue of God, and of the looue of our neighbour? Dooth it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooue our body which is the temple of God, to be prophaned? That our eares whiche were created of God to hear his voice ſhould be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped againſt it, and be open to vanities, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton talk and vnchaſte worldly ſonges? Dooth it behooue our tung which is bound by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right of creation, to ſing the praiſes of God, &amp; by the right of redemption to ſhew foorth the Lords death til he come<note n="8" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> that this tung which is ſo proper an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the glory of God, ſhold be mute to goodnes, and inceſſantly occupyed in backbiting, ſlandering, blaſpheming, or at the leaſt in ſpeaking idle words, wherof one day we ſhall yéeld an accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before the throne of the maieſtie of God?<note n="9" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36.</note> Dooth it behooue our mouth which ought to receiue the bleſſed ſigne of the body &amp; blood of our Lord Ieſus to to ſuppreſſe the benefit of our redemption &amp; to haue Adders poiſon in it? Dooth it behooue our
<pb facs="tcp:7035:14"/>hand which ought to take at the Supper the aſſured gage of the looue of God, the infallible pledges of his legue with vs, the erneſt peny of our ſaluation, to be void of goodneſſe, and be ſide that, be giuen to extortion, theft, murder, oppreſſion and violence? Dooth it behooue our féet which ought to run &amp; make haſte to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to be redy and light to run to miſchéef? No ſurely but as he which calleth vs is holy,<note n="10" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 11.44 <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.7. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.75 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.38</note> ſo likewiſe muſt we alſo be wholly holy, as he hath brought vs by holy baptiſme into his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly houſe which is his Church, the communion of Saints: euen ſo likewiſe muſt we leade therin a good &amp; holy conuerſation, as he hath waſhed vs from our ſinnes, by the pretious blood of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte: ſo muſt we dye to them, and liue in righteouſnes, as he hath called vs to the incorruptible hope of the bleſſed reſurrection and eternall life: ſo muſt we lift vp our harts on hye, and not be bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like Moules in this frail and tranſitory Earth. To be ſhort, ſéeing that the grace of God is ſet before vs euery day, and his holy woord ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in our eares<note n="11" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2 11 12.13.14.</note> to this only end that it may be ſaluation vnto vs, and that (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing all vngodlines and worldly deſires) we ſhould liue ſoberly, iuſtly, &amp; godly in this preſent world, looking for the bleſſed hope and appéering of the glory of the mightie God,
<pb facs="tcp:7035:14"/>and of our Saueour Ieſus Chriſte: we muſt pray vnto this good God, that he would giue vs grace ſo to behaue our ſelues towards him in liuing godly, ſo towardꝭ our neighbours, in liuing iuſtly, ſo towards our ſelues, in liuing ſoberly: that we may be found at the day irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prenſible, by the meanes of that his wel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looue Sonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>Of thanks giuing. Article. 3.</head>
               <p>THirdly we muſt giue thanks to this good God for the benefit of our redemption, and for this cauſe it is that the auncients cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the holly Supper, <hi>Euchariſtie,</hi> that is to ſay, gratefulnes, good grace, giuing of thanks. For if ſo be that our ordinary food, and dayly bread whiche God giueth vs for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our bodyes, ought to be ſanctified by the word,<note n="1" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 5.</note> and receiued with thankꝭ giuing: ought we not much more to thank God for the heauenly bread, and for the nouriſhment of our ſoules which is offered vnto vs and really giuen vs in the holy ſupper of Ieſus Chriſte?</p>
               <p>And we ſée alſo how Ieſus Chriſte him ſelf ſheweth vs an example héerof. For when he took the bread of the Supper, <hi>S. Mathevv</hi>
                  <note n="2" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.22.</note> and <hi>S. Mark</hi> ſay, that Ieſus Chriſte bleſſed. And <hi>S. Luke</hi> expoundeth this woord to bleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:7035:15"/>when he ſaith that he gaue<note n="3" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.19.</note> thanks. Now then, ſéeing that we ſée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ieſus Chriſte when he tooke the bread of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Supper gaue thankꝭ to God his Father, as he did alſo when he took the cup<note n="4" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 26.27. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.17.</note> and that for the redemption of man kinde: it is our duty to doo the like. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better mooued to giue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks to God: we haue to conſider the greatnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefit of our redemption &amp; the excellency of the gift which God giueth vs at this holy table, which cannot be doon: vnleſſe we conſider our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, which was before figured by the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall captiuite of <hi>Egipt.</hi> We ſée there how <hi>Pharaoh</hi>
                  <note n="5" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.</note> was ſtrong &amp; mightie, how he knew not the eternall, how he went about to kil all the ſéed of the <hi>Iſraelits,</hi> by the ſuppre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion &amp; death of their men children, we ſee alſo how exceſſiuely he cauſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to woork without any hope of wages, how he wold not ſuffer them by any meanes to ſacrifice to the Lord, nor to go foorth of the land of <hi>Egipt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which thing continued not for one yéer or two: but for the ſpace of foure hundred &amp; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<note n="6" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> 12.20.</note> yéeres. Heer may we liuely beholde a draught of our miſery. We were all loſt and deſtroyed in Adam. We were holden cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues in the helly <hi>Egipt</hi> vnder the tiranny of a ſpirituall <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> which is the Deuil.</p>
               <p>This tirant was ſtrong and mightie: he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred
<pb facs="tcp:7035:15"/>vs not to ſerue our God. He made vs to labour inceſſantly in ſlauiſh and vnfrutefull woorks of ſin to the eſtabliſhment of his owne kingdome. He flew not onely our men Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: but he led vs all indiferently, to vtter ruin and deſtruſtion. And this tiranny bad not onely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued for a certain time: but had béen eternall and for euer parmanent, if the mercy and power of our God had not plucked vs out of it by the miniſtery of the true <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> which is our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, who is the true Lamb whiche the heauenly Father hath deliuered to death, to deliuer vs from it and purchaſe vs eternal life. As it is ſaid, that God ſo looued the world: that he hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his only begotten ſonne<note n="7" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.16.</note> that who ſoeuer belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in him ſhould not periſh, but haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. Now then, ſeeing this good God hath doon in vs ſo great a pleaſure, as to frée vs from the tiranny of the Deuil, of ſinne, of death, of hel: ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> his looue was ſo great that he deliuered his onely Sonne to the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el and ignominious death of the croſſe, for vs which were the ſeruants and bond ſlaues of Sathan: his welbelooued for vs whiche were his enemies: the iuſt, and the Lamb without ſpot, for vs which were ſinners and corrupt: the onely heir of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> for vs which were worthely heires of hel: ought we not tobe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed
<pb facs="tcp:7035:16"/>with admiration of this great and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable looue of God towards vs, and our tungs tobe for euer diſplayed to publiſh with loud voice the praiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefit of our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? It is very reſonable, and therfore we ſée that Ieſus Chriſte admoniſheth vs of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this behalf, ſpeaking of the ſelebration of the holy Supper.<note n="8" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.19. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24.</note> Doo this in remembrance of me. And <hi>S. Paule</hi> expreſſeth what remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce this is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he aduertiſeth vs,<note n="9" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.</note> that as often as we ſhall eat this bread, &amp; drink this cup: we ſhew the Lords death til he come.</p>
               <p>Seeing then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God requireth of vs a true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging of his benefits whiche we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue at his hands &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifulnes, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> menes of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: let vs take héed that we be not ſpotted with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fault of in gratitude, eſpecially if we will not incur the wrathfull diſpleaſure of God and acknowledge him for Iudge, whome we would not acknowledge for a gentle and merciful father, as <hi>S. Paule</hi> alſo to this purpoſe thretneth the ingrate and forgetful, when he ſaith, whoſoeuer ſhall eate this bread and drinck the cup of the Lord vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthely: eateth and drinketh his owne dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. And rightfully is the vengeance of God diſplayed againſt them which wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of God, in that that concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth their owne ſaluation. For if ſo be that a
<pb facs="tcp:7035:16"/>murderer redy to be hanged for his wicked déeds caſting away &amp; reiecting his Princes gratious pardon (&amp; not vouchſauing to thank him for it) deſerueth worthely the gallous, or if a Childe deſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rod, for not giuing once I thank you to his father, when he hath recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued at his hands great and ſinguler benefits, much more we whiche for our ſinful and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked déeds deſerue tobe hanged in hel, if we contemne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God our ſouerain prince, and make no count of this euerlaſting bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, which our heuenly father preſenteth vs withall in Ieſus Chriſte, who is offered to vs in the Supper, by good right &amp; reaſon we are worthy to periſh for our vnkindenes and vnthankfulnes. But héer muſt we diligently mark the points that folowe.</p>
               <p>Firſt this acknowledging muſt be made to one only God by his only ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. For euen as God by his onely ſonne hath cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated vs, &amp; redéemed vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting death: ſo wil he that to him alone, &amp; by him alone, in whome he is wel pleaſed: we render thanks for all his benefits. As we ſée how <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth this foorth vnto vs in many places, and preciſely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> where he ſaith. Bleſſed be God euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, whiche hath bleſſed vs with all his ſpirituall bleſſing in Heaueuly
<pb facs="tcp:7035:17"/>things in Chriſte as he hath choſen vs in him before the foundation of the world, but they which call vpon Saints and put their truſt in them, or in their merits, they alſo whiche make them patrons and aduocates to God warde, and like wiſe they whiche truſt in their owne ſtrength, in their owne frée will or good woorks: rob God of his glory, and can not giue him true thanks for the benefit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. For we cannot giue to any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the leaſt iot that may be in the matter of our ſaluation: but wee commit ſacriledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God the creator. And therfore renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing our ſelues and euery liuing creature: let vs ſay with the Apoſtle<note n="10" place="margin">1. <hi>Ti.</hi> 1.17.</note> vnto the King e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting, immortall, inuiſible, vnto God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſe, be honor and glory for euer and euer Amen.</p>
               <p>Secondly thanks muſt be giuen not with the mouth only: but with the hart alſo. For ſéeing that God is a ſpirit: he riquireth a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of vs, that is agréeable to his nature, that is to ſay, he wil be ſerued of vs in ſpirit and trueth. And therfore when that praiſing of God for the benefit of redemption, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in queſtion: we muſt haue our harts lift vp on hye, and there muſt be a conſent and mutuall agréement betwéen our inwarde affections and our tungs, as we ſée how <hi>Dauid</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:7035:17"/>himſelf to the ſame, when he ſaith.<note n="11" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1</note> My ſoule praiſe thou the Lord &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is within me praiſe his holy na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. My ſoule (I ſay) praiſe thou y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, &amp; forget not all his benefits. And the bleſſed Virgin ſingeth the ſelf ſame in her ſong, ſaying<note n="12" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.46.</note> My ſoule magnifieth the Lord, and my ſpirit reioyceth in God my Saueour, now, all hipocrits, and wicked perſons, alſo they that ſing &amp; praiſe in an vnknowen tung, are héer reprooued. For where there is no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: ther is no affection nor wil, and conſequently no Faith, without which: what ſoeuer we doo be it neuer ſo faire and glorious before men, it is but ſinne and abhomination before God. Let vs take héed therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in this be half we wander not and go aſtray, leſt we be condemned with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Ievvish</hi> people whiche honored and ſerued God in vain, in ſo muche as they came néer vnto him onely with their mouthes,<note n="13" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 29.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8.</note> and honoured him with their lips, but not with their harts.</p>
               <p>Thirdly it muſt be doon at all times and ſeaſons, that is to ſay, aſwel in affliction: as in proſperitie, and to this purpoſe <hi>Dauid</hi> proteſteth.<note n="14" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 34.1</note> That hée will alwaye giue thanks vnto his Lord, and that his praiſe ſhal be in his mouth continually. And <hi>Saint Paule</hi> admoniſheth the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> to<note n="15" place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5 18.</note> giue thanks in all things: adding, for this is the wil of God in Chriſte Ieſus. But this is clene
<pb facs="tcp:7035:18"/>contrary to time ſeruers, and to all them whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in time of proſperitie fawne vpon the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and are well content for that time to praiſe God whome afterwarde in time of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction they defye and ſet naught by.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of this miſchéef is, for that they haue not yéelded them ſelues to the Churche of God for a good end and purpoſe, as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll the glory of God, to ſéek their owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and the ſaluation of their brethern, but rather to greaten them ſelues in their goods and honours, and to ſatiſfye their owne affections. And therfore it commeth to paſſe that as ſoon as the deuil lifteth vp his hornes againſt the Churche of God, and perſcutions be at hand: they melt away by and by in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as dooth War before the fire, they are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and parched with the Sunne of the Croſſe, they are ſory for the good they haue doon, they repent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues that they were ſo haſty to confeſſe the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte in the aſſembly of the faithful, they wiſh they had neuer knowen God nor his woord, nor his Church, nor his miniſters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they make greter account (as <hi>Eſau</hi> did) of one meſſe of pottage<note n="16" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.38.</note> then of the birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and bleſſing of the heauenly father, But let ſuch maner of perſons knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it ſhall no more profit them, that they made a fair begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:7035:18"/>&amp; ioly holding vp of their buckler: then it did <hi>Cain, Eſau, Saule, Iudas.</hi> For ſéeing that ſentence is generall, that whoſoeuer continueth vnto the end he ſhalbe ſaued: it foloweth by the contrary y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all they whiche doo not coutinue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly in the confeſſion of the ſonne of God, &amp; are hindred by their goods and honours, looue of the world, eaſe of their fleſh, to ſet foorth &amp; declare with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual train, the benefit of our redemption: it foloweth (I ſay) that ſuch perſons ſhall go to ruin and euerlaſting deſtruction Laſt of all, this acknowledging muſt not onely bee priuat: but publique, in the face and preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the whole church, and therfore as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith<note n="17" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12 13.14.</note> what ſhall I render vnto the Lord for all his benefits toward me? I wil take the cup of ſaluation and call vpon the name of the Lord. I wil pay my vowes vnto the Lord, euen now in the preſence of all his people. And again,<note n="18" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.9.10.</note> I haue declared thy righteouſnes in the great congregation, to I haue not refrained my lips, O Lord thou knoweſt, I haue not hid thy righteouſneſſe within mine hart, but I haue declared thy trueth and thy ſaluation, I haue not concea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led thy mercy &amp; thy trueth from the great congregation. So then this ought tobe wel printed in the hart of the weke, and thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:7035:19"/>that are aſhamed to confeſſe &amp; praiſe open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our Lord Ieſus Chriſte. For ſéeing that God dooth auouche vs openly for his people &amp; he giueth him ſelf fréely vnto vs, &amp; to our children, in the perſon of his wel belooued ſonne our Lord Ieſꝰ Chriſte: we can doo no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auouch him publiquely for our god and ſaueour, in the perſon of that ſame his welbelooued ſonne Chriſte Ieſus our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>¶ Of Looue. Article. 4.</head>
               <p>FAith, Repentance, and acknowledging of Gods benefits, cannot haue place in vs, and in vain are we called Chriſtians, or that we brag of our ſelues for the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the commaundements of the firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which concerne the ſeruice of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned: vnleſſe we ſhew the effects by the keeping of the commaundements of the ſecond Table, which concerne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> looue of our neighbour, without whiche alſo we cannot worthely preſent our ſelues to the holy Table of Ieſus Chriſte our Lord. And therfore is it that Ieſus Chriſte him ſelf in the ſermon of the Supper which hee made to his Apoſtles the ſame night that he was betrayed and deliuered to death for vs, did diligently beat this point into their heads, ſaying.<note n="1" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh</hi> 13.35.</note> By this ſhall all men knowe that
<pb facs="tcp:7035:19"/>ye army Diſciples, if ye haue looue one to au other. And again,<note n="2" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.12.13.14.</note> This is my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement that ye looue one an other, as I haue looued you. Greater looue then this hath no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when any man beſtoweth his life for his Fréends. Ye are my fréends: if ye doo what ſo euer I commaund you. To this ſame end tendeth alſo that, that the ſame night Ieſus Chriſte waſhed the féete of his Apoſtles,<note n="3" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.12.13.14, 15.</note> acter which waſhing: he ſaid vnto them, knowe ye what I haue doon to you? ye call me Maiſter and Lord, and ye ſay wel, for ſo I am, If I then your Lord and Maiſter haue waſhed your feet: ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ought to waſh one an others féet. For I haue giuen you an example that yee ſhould doo euen as I haue doon do you.</p>
               <p>We muſt therfore (according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement and example of the ſonne of God) be furniſhed with true and hot looue, that we may worthely preſent our ſelues to the Lords table. If we wil haue a true diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cription of this looue: we muſt take it of <hi>S, Paule,</hi> which pointeth it out in liuely cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, writing to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Corinthians</hi> in this ſort.<note n="4" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4.</note> Looue (ſaith he) ſuffereth long, it is boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiful, looue enuieth not, looue dooth not boaſt it ſelf, it is not puffed vp, it diſdayneth not, it ſéeketh not her owne things, it is not
<pb facs="tcp:7035:20"/>prouoked to anger, it thinketh not euill, it reioyceth not in iniquitie, but reioyceth in the trueth. It ſuffereth all things, it belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth all things, it hopeth all things, it indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all things. Sée what manner of looue ours ought tobe, euery one of vs muſt inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour that all the partes of this deſcription may rightly agrée vnto vs. We are many waies and in ſundry ſorts exhorted to this looue and brotherly concord in the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte. Firſt in that that we muſt wait one for an other,<note n="5" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.35</note> and that it is not lawful for euery one of vs to celebrate the Supper perticulerly and a parte: but when the whole congregation is aſſembled togither, all the faithful togither muſt take, eate and drink, the Bread and wine of the Supper, according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of Ieſus Chriſte.<note n="6" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.21. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.19. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14</note> Take ye eate ye, and drink ye all of this. It is a true figure and teſtimonie of the vnitie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ought tobe among vs. Moreouer in that that wée béeing all gethered togither in one houſe of God, which is his Churche, we doo there all call vpon one ſelf ſame Father which is in Heauen, we haue all one ſelf ſame hed, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate and interceſſour, whiche is Ieſus Chriſte:<note n="7" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 12. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.17. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.</note> we are all quickened with his holy Spirit which dwelleth in vs, in that
<pb facs="tcp:7035:20"/>that we all haue one ſelf ſame word of God, in that that we all eat of one ſelf ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall meat, and drinck all of the ſelf ſame ſpirituall drink, in that alſo that we all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend as Brethren to one ſelf ſame inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whiche is the kingdome of He auen: ought not this inflame vs with true and hot looue? Finally, the making of the bread and wine of the Supper dooth teach vs aſſo what vnitie and concord we ought to haue one with an other, for as we ſée, that the bread is made of many cornes, and yet not withſtanding afterwards is but one ſelfe ſame lump of Bread: as we ſee alſo that the Wine is made of many cluſters of grapes, and yet after it is made, is but one onely wine: in like ſort muſt the Chriſtians whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are many in them ſelues: be ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither thorow looue into one body, which is the Church, wherof Ieſus Chriſte ought to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be the onely hed and leader. But we muſt note that this looue wherunto we are exhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by ſo many reaſons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Supper, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be where there is enuy, brauling, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, rancour, debate &amp; diuiſion: and therfore before we com to the Supper, (whiche is a witneſſe of our agréement aſwel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt as with his congregation) if we haue had a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſtrife and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention with our brethern:
<pb facs="tcp:7035:21"/>we muſt loouingly reconſile our ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. If any man haue offended vs: wée muſt frankly and fréely forgiue our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <note n="8" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23.44.</note> yea our enemies, as we would that that good God ſhould pardon vs, and as wée ſée how Ieſus Chriſt our Lord hath left vs an example of this looue: when he prayed to God his father for his enemies whiche put him to death,<note n="9" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc</hi> 23.34.</note> as we rede alſo that <hi>S. Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> did the ſame.<note n="10" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 7.60.</note> Again, we muſt alſo mark, that this looue ought tobe practiſed in all eſtates. Kings muſt looue their ſubiects, they muſt be Nurces<note n="11" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.23.</note> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of God, loouers of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon peace, they muſt vſe their people with all moderation and clemency. So likewiſe muſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people honor the king,<note n="12" place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.13.14.15. <hi>Ro.</hi> 13.2.3</note> they muſt pay him their tribute faithful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, they muſt be obedient to all his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and Officers. The Paſtour muſt looue his flock,<note n="13" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.31 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2.3.</note> he muſt watch, take pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and pray inceſſantly for it.<note n="14" place="margin">1. <hi>Sa</hi> 12.13</note> So like wiſe muſt the ſhéep looue their paſtour, the Fathers their children, the Children their fathers and Mothers, the Wife the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and the Huſband the wife, the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters their ſeruants, &amp; the Seruants their maiſters, and euery one in his calling muſt indeuer to exerciſe looue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vocation whervnto God hath called him. For other
<pb facs="tcp:7035:21"/>wiſe it wilbe impoſſible for vs to doo our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties faithfully, aſwel toward god: as toward men, if the rule of looue doo not guide and gouern vs in all our dooings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>Article. 5. Neceſſary obſeruations for them that wil come to the Lords table.</head>
               <p>IN the articles aforeſaid, conſiſteth the true examining of our ſelues, notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding we muſt take good héed to theſe points and notes which folow.</p>
               <p>Firſt we haue to note, that we muſt not raſt our heds and bend our braines to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine curiouſly an other mannes life: as many doo, whiche ſtretch out and ſcanne ſo narowly the blemiſhes of their Brethren, that they forget their owne. It is to be wiſhed, and we muſt procure it aſmuch as lyeth in vs, that the Church of God may be maintained in puritie, without ſhew of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. But for ſo muche as in this worlde Corne ſhall alwaies be mixed with chaffe,<note n="1" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12.</note> wéeds with whete,<note n="2" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.24.</note> good fiſh with bad,<note n="3" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.47.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> with true Apoſtles,<note n="4" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.</note> fooliſh Virgins with wiſe,<note n="5" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.25.</note> yet none of vs muſt be offended therfore, and moreouer let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man indeuour to finde that perfection in him ſelf, which he deſireth to bring into
<pb facs="tcp:7035:22"/>an other.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we muſt not think that faith, repentance, giuiuing of thanks &amp; looue, and other vertues which God requireth of vs, can be perfet héer in this world, for there wil be alwaies in vs, (what rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>erate and new borne ſo euer we be) ſome remnants of ſinne, of incredulitie, of lacke of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, of vnthankfulneſſe, and of ſelflooue, which is directly contrary and oppoſite, to the true looue of our neighboure. As long as we liue, the fleſh<note n="6" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 7.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.6.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1.1. <hi>Pe.</hi> 5.8.</note> wil fight againſt the Spirite, the Deuill and the Worlde, wil make war againſt vs as the life of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches, Prophets and Apoſtles doo ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ently witneſſe vnto vs, ſo that euen to the laſt breath of our life, we ſhall haue néed to craue of our God that he would forgiue vs our ſinnes through his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Notwitſtanding ſo far it is that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections which are in vs ſhould cauſe vs to drawe back from God and from this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly banquet: that rather (ſo that we are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with our ſelues for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) they ought to cauſe vs to come the ſooner, to the intent that as poore famiſhed creatures: we might more gréedily and with greater deſire, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Ieſus Chriſte, which is the true ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd of our ſoules.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7035:22"/>
               <p>Thirdly, although it be not required to the worthy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the Supper, to haue a perfit faith, perfit repentance, perfit gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of thanks, perfit looue: yet muſt they be (notwithſtanding) true, and procéed from the hart and from the Spirit. Our faith muſt not be fained, our repentaunce muſt not be counterfait and painted, as that of Hipocrites: the thanks whiche we giue to God muſt not come onely from the mouth, neither muſt we loue our brethren in word only, and not in déed: but let the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our faith, and chriſten life, abooue all things be far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oſtententation &amp; hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we take more paines to be good Chriſtians in déed and before God: then to be ſo counted and taken before men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <head>¶ Againſt them that vvillingly and of ſet purpoſe abſtain from the holy Supper of the Lord. Article. 6.</head>
               <p>AS there are many which doo amis in preſenting them ſelues vnworthyly to the communion: ſo there are many which doo amiſſe on the contrary ſide, in that they wil by no meanes come, nor preſent them ſelues to this holy banquet. For feare of communicating (as they ſay) vnworthyly,
<pb facs="tcp:7035:23"/>and ſo conſequently tobe culpable of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood of Ieſus Chriſte. But let them that ſo abſtain of ſet purpoſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lords holy table: knowe that it is no leſſe fault vp on an vnthankfulneſſe, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from the holy and ſacred meats whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che God preſenteth to vs at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Supper: then to receiue it vnworthely, as we ſee that a Patient which beeing very ſick maketh no account of the receipt and dyet whiche the Phiſition hath preſcribed: is no leſſe faulty then he which abuſeth, or vſeth it not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petently, as the Phiſition hath appointed.</p>
               <p>Therefore let not this ſort of people flat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter them ſelues, as though by this meanes they could be excuſed bothe before God and men, ſéeing that it is a moſt certain trueth, that ſo haynous an ingratitude, is in no wiſe tobe admitted, or worthy excuſe. For firſt of all, ſuch men doo willingly contemn the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Ieſus Chriſt, which ſaith to all his, doo this, take ye eat ye.</p>
               <p>Secondly they contemne the bleſſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the death and paſſion of the Sonne of God, who commaundeth all the faithful to ſelebrate the Supper in remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance of him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they contemne the price of their redemption, that is to ſay, the pretious body
<pb facs="tcp:7035:23"/>and blood of Ieſus Chriſte, which are giuen and diſtributed to all faithful Chriſtians in the Supper according as it is ſaid. This is my body, which is giuen for you, this, is my blood which is ſhed for the remiſſion of your ſinnes. Finally, they deſpiſe the church and the vnitie therof, and willingly excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate them ſelues from the Communion whiche the faithful haue in the Supper, as wel with Ieſus Chriſte: as one with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. We ſée therfore how fondly theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of the Lords holy Supper doo fall, and ar vtterly inexcuſable. And therfore let vs take good héed that we folowe them not, if we wil not be puniſhed with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which for their Oxen<note n="1" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.7. <hi>Luc.</hi> 14.22</note> Fermes, Wines, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique of merchandiſe refuſed to come to the mariage in the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="article">
               <head>Contrarywiſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which come vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to the holy Supper of the Lord, or ought not be therunto admitted. Article. 7.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of them vvhich ſin againſt the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the firſt preparation, which conſiſteth in true faith,</head>
                  <p>ALl <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> that is, ſuch as are with out God, miſbeléeuers, ignorant of God &amp; his woord, all heretiques &amp; falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb facs="tcp:7035:24"/>all Magicians, Idolaters, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, whiche are partakers of the tables of Deuils, likewiſe all they which haue but an hiſtoricall Faith, all the adherents &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Roomiſh Antichriſt, and they that eſtabliſh by any maner (whatſoeuer) his kingdome, or depend there on, alſo all they which haue not yelded them ſelues to the Church of God, and haue not made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their Faith, finally all they that cuſtomably ſwere, either by the name of God or by their Faith, and apply it to vain matters, and cauſes of no value, all theſe ought to abſtain from the Lords Table, for ſo muche as they haue not a true truſt in God, without the whiche we can not bée members of Ieſus Chriſte, nor conſequent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly bee apt and méete to receiue life of him, which is the onely hed of the true faithfull.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of them which ſin againſt the ſecond Article of the ſecond preparation which conſiſteth in Repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance.</head>
                  <p>ALl they which liue ſlanderouſly, all impenitent and vnthrifts, all contem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners of God, of his woord and of his holy aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, all blaſphemers and denyers of the name of God, all deſpiſers of correction and eccleſiaſtical diſcipline, they alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:7035:24"/>and frequent ordinarily euil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, which walke in the counſel of the wicked<note n="1" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1 1.</note> which ſtand in the way of ſinners, which ſit in the ſeat of the ſcorneful. To be ſhort, they in whome appéereth no amendment of life, no regeneration, and they that conimit hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and infamous vices, and ſuch as are tobe puniſhed by the magiſtrate, all theſe, after that they are knowen tobe ſuch: ought not tobe admitted to the ſupper, and if they preſent them ſelues vnto it: they ought not tobe receiued, leſt that that is holy be giuen to Dogs and Swine,<note n="2" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6.</note> to the great diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and ſlander of his Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of them which ſin againſt the third Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticle of the third preparation which conſiſteth in giuing of thanks.</head>
                  <p>WIithout true faith and repentance: we cannot be méet to ſet forth the pariſes of God, who wil not be prayſed by the mouth of the wicked,<note n="3" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16.</note> &amp; therfore all Infidels, Igno rants and impenitent, ſin alſo againſt this Article, and ought not tobe receiued to the Lords Supper. Alſo they that are mad or fooles, either by nature or ſome other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. They alſo which by reaſon that they be vnder age (as little childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) can not ſhew foorth the Lords death til he come, are not
<pb facs="tcp:7035:25"/>capable of the Supper.</p>
                  <p>Finally, they which by fragilitie, vnkind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, and contempt, in time of perſecution did forſake Gods cauſe, and renounce the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, ought not alſo tobe admitted thither: vnleſſe that they doo firſt make open confeſſion of their fault, and be reconciled to the Church of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of them which ſin againſt the fourth article of the fourth preparation whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che conſiſteth in Looue toward our neighbours.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He diſobedient to Father and mother, to the magiſtrate, &amp; to al ſuperiours, the ſeditious conſpiratours, fighters, murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and ſuch as bere malice and hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their neighbours, they that are cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away with a deſire of reuengement, whoremongers, adulterers, incontinent bougerers, drunkards, and gluttons, decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, couetous, théeues, and vſurers, backbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, mockers, falſe witneſſes, lyers, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon periured perſons, and in ſum, all they which make an art of the breach of looue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their neighbours, contained in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cond table of the law of God, ought not tobe receiued to the Supper. For ſeéing that the Scripture pronounceth thus, that ſuche ſort
<pb facs="tcp:7035:25"/>of men haue none, acquaintance of God, are ſhut out of the kingdome of Heauen,<note n="4" place="margin">Ephe. <hi>5.5.</hi> Pſal. <hi>15.</hi>
                     </note> and ſhall not dwel in the Lords holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: they ought of right tobe ſhut out from theſe ſacred ſignes, wherby the faithful are ioyned to Ieſus Chriſte and made poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſors of eternall life.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <head>
               <hi>A Dialogue of the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to the holy Supper of our Lord IESVS CHRISTE.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>¶</hi> The Father.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owe muſt wée be prepared to come worthely to the ſupper of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Childe.</speaker>
               <p>We muſt examin our ſelues according to the precept of the holy Apoſtle <hi>S. Paule.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Wherin conſiſteth the eramination of our ſelues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>In two points. Firſt, that we behaue ourſelues as it is méet towarde God, who calleth vs to this holy banquet.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>Then that we doo our dutye to our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren which are called to this holy Table with vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7035:26"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What is our duty towards God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth principally in three points</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Which are they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>In faith, repentance &amp; giuing of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What is faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It is a certaine aſſurance that God is our father and Saueour in the name of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſte our Lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>This aſſurance, commeth it of vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>1.</hi> Iohn. <hi>17.</hi> Rom <hi>10.</hi> Rom. <hi>8.</hi> Gala. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> for the faithfull are not borne of fleſh, nor blood: neither of the wil of man, but they are borne of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>But what meanes dooth God vſe to beget vs vnto him, and to giue vs faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>His woord confirmed in vs by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woork of the holy Ghoſt, who cryeth in our harts <hi>Abba,</hi> that is to ſay, father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Is not this faith confirmed and raty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in vs by the Lords Supper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>How ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt of all in that that Ieſus Chriſte giueth himſelf vnto vs, promiſing vs that his body was giuen to death for vs, and that his blood was ſhed for the remiſſion of our ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>In that that the bread and wine whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we take, eate, and drink, according to
<pb facs="tcp:7035:26"/>Gods inſtitution, teache vs that through faith we take, eate, and drink the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſte, for the nouriſhment of our ſoules.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>And thoſe that are Inſidels, can they eate the body of Ieſus Chriſte, and drinck his blood?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No, becauſe they haue no true Faith, without which we can not be members of Ieſus Chriſte, nor conſequently receiue life of him who is the only hed of the faithful.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What then doo the Infidels whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they receiue the Sacrament of the Supper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>They eat and drink their owne dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> in ſted of receiuing the pledges and gages of their ſalnation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Where muſt the true faithful ſéek Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, to inioy him, and to haue the fruition of him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>In heauen. For if we be riſen again with Chriſte:<note place="margin">Colo. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> we muſt ſéek the things that are on hye, where Chriſte is ſitting on the right hand of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Is not this the matter that the aunei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Biſhops vſed in the celebration of the Supper, to ſay to the people, <hi>Surſum corda,</hi> that is, lift vp your harts?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes. And therfore the people anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Habemus ad Dominum.</hi> We haue
<pb facs="tcp:7035:27"/>them to the Lord. Now that Ieſus Chriſt is in Heauen and we on earth: how can wée be ioyned &amp; vnite or made one with him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>By faith and by the woork of the holy Ghoſt, whiche can wel ioyne and knit that that is otherwiſe ſeperated by diſtance of place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhall we then ſay of them that ſéek Ieſus Chriſte in the Elements of the Supper, and ſay that there is a Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation of the bread and wine, into the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>They erre diuers and ſundry waies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F,</speaker>
               <p>How ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, they ſpeake againſt thrée Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our Beleef, that is, that Ieſus Chriſt is aſcended vp into Heauen, that he ſitteth on the right hand of God, and that he ſhall not depart from thence til he come to iudge vothe the quick and the dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>By their tranſubſtantiation alſo they aboliſh the ſigne of the Sacrament, that is to ſay, the bread and the wine, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently they aboliſh the Sacrament of the Supper, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be without the ſigne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>This doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation hath it no other abſurdities?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C,</speaker>
               <p>Yes, for it giueth holy thingꝭ to ſwine,
<pb facs="tcp:7035:27"/>and graniteth, that the Inſidels may eat Ieſus Chriſte. Moreouer it maketh men Idotaters, and cauſeth them to worſhip the Sactament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Say on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It maketh alſo the glorious body of Ieſus Chriſte ſubiect to rotting and filth.</p>
               <p>Tobe ſhort it aboliſheth the true humanity of the ſonne of God, making him an infinit body, and ſuch an one as is in all places.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>But hath not Ieſus Chriſte ſaid,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>28.</hi> Math. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> that he would be with vs vnto the ende of the world: and where as two or three ſhould bee gathered togither in his name, there hee would be in the middeſt of them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes. But theſe places muſt be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the preſence of his diuinitie, and not of his humanitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>How canſt thou prooue that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>By the witnaſſe of Ieſus Chriſte him ſelf (whiche ſaith) that wee ſhall alwayes haue the poore with vs:<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>12.</hi> Ict. <hi>3.21.</hi>
                  </note> but him we ſhal not haue alwaies, and <hi>S. Peeter</hi> ſaith, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen muſt contain Ieſus Chriſte, vntil the reſtoring of all things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Therfore thou wilt conclude, that although Ieſus Chriſt by his diuinitie, and his holy Spirite be alwaies with vs: yet notwithſtanding touching his humanitie
<pb facs="tcp:7035:28"/>he can be but in one certain place, that is in Heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yea,<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>2.</hi> Pſal. <hi>54.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> alſo witneſſeth ſaying. Vntil heauen be ended, the Lord ſhalbe alwaies on hie. But the trueth of the Lord is alſo with vs For his body wherein he was raiſed: muſt needs be in one certain place, but his trueth is ſpread throughout.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What is the ſumme of this true faith which ſeeketh not Ieſus Chriſte in Earth, but in Heauen?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I beléeue in God whiche hath created me, I beléeue in Ieſus Chriſte which hath redeemed me from ſin, from Sathan, from Hel and from death, I beleeue alſo in the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, which hath ſanctified me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſaieſt thou perticulerly, I bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and not we beleeue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe that euery one muſt examin himſelf,<note place="margin">Hab. <hi>2.</hi> Rom. <hi>1.</hi> Gala. <hi>3.</hi> Hev. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> and liue by his owne faith, and not by the faith of other men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>How muſt that be doon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>When we doo euery man particuler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for him ſelf apply Ieſus Chriſte vnto him ſelf with all his bleſſings and riches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What riches are there in Ieſꝰ Chriſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>There is ſaluation for the loſt, life for the dead trueth for the liers, wiſdoine for the ignoraunt, Iuſtice for the ſinners, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification
<pb facs="tcp:7035:28"/>ctification for the impure ones, redemption for the captiues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Muſt we therfore by faith applye all theſe things vnto vs, ſéeing we are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture loſt, dead, lyers, ignorant, ſinners, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clene and captiues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, for Ieſus Chriſte hath taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him all our miſeryes and wretche ones, to giue and communicate vnto vs all his bleſſings and riches, as alſo in deéd they be diſtributed vnto vs in his holy Supper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs now ſpeak of the ſecond parte of our duty towards God, which conſiſteth in repentance, and firſt of all what repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It is a ſorowfulnes and hafred of euil and a looue of that that is good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Tobe ſory and gréeued for our wicked neſſe, is it not neceſſary to knowe it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>How doo we know the euil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is in vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt of all by our beginning for that that is borne of fleſh is fleſh. Secondly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we tranſgreſſe the law of God, which is the rule of all perfection &amp; Iuſtice. Third ly by the ordinary afflictions, whiche God ſendeth vs becauſe of our ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Haue we not alſo the Sacraments a glaſſe to beholde our ſinnes in?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:7035:29"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>We haue ſo. For is we were not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: we ſhould haue no néed of remiſſion of our ſinnes in Baptiſme. And if we were not in death it were in vain for vs to come to the Supper, to ſéek life and ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>When we knowe our ſinnes, ought we not confeſſe them before God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>32.</hi> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Lut. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> According to the example of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid and the <hi>Publican,</hi> if we wil be iuſtified before God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſhould we confeſſe and acknow ſedge our ſinnes before God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>To obfain parden and ful remiſſion, as God is iuſt and faithful to doo it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>For what end and purpoſe dooth God pardon vs our ſinnes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C,</speaker>
               <p>For thrée principall ends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What are they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt to this end, that we ſhould recon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cile our ſelues to our enemyes, ſecondly, that we ſhould forgiue them, thyrdly that we ſhould abſtain from ſinne, and liue to righteouſnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Is there nothing in the Supper, that exhorteth vs to flée and hate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, for in that that wee breake the bread of the Supper: it ſheweth vs that our ſinnes did brute and breake the Sonne of
<pb facs="tcp:7035:29"/>God with the ſorowes of death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What foloweth then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That we ſhould condemne and deteſt our ſinnes, as the Authoures of the death of the Sonne of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Is it ſufficient to abſtaine from euill, and not to doo good?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No, for euery trée that bringeth not foorth good frute:<note place="margin">Math. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; <hi>5</hi> Mat. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> is cut down and caſt into the fyre. And therfore the naughtie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was caſt into vtter darkneſſe, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had wickedly ſpent his Maiſters Talent, but becauſe he vſed it not nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is therfore requiſit that euery one according to the talent which he hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God: doo glorify him in that vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherunto he is called.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yea. If we wil enter as the good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, into the ioy of our Maiſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>To doo this goodnes, muſt we not haue knoweledge?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By what meanes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>By the law of God, and generally by all the holy Scriptures, whiche ſhew vnto vs what the good woorks are, whiche God requireth of vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Are we not exhorted to the Supper,
<pb facs="tcp:7035:30"/>to liue wel?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that we are. For in that that we are made one with Ieſꝰ Chriſte, made fleſh of his fleſh and bones of his bones, further more in that that we are partakers of his holineſſe and innocency: it is to this end, that we ſhould be holy as he is holy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>In that alſo that we méet and agrée in the holy Church, which is the communion of Saints, in that that by the opperation and woork of the holy Ghoſt: we call vpon one father which is holy, to be ſhort, in that that we hear his holy woord, and receine his holy Sacraments: it ought alſo to mooue vs to holyneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>This holyneſſe which God requireth of vs, is it perfit in this world?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No. As the examples of the Saincts ſhew vs. And moreouer vnto the laſt breth of our life, we ſhall haue alwaies need to aſke of God that he would forgiue vs our ſinnes through his Sonne Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>And this holyneſſe which is not perfit, can it pleaſe God which is parfit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yea. For ſo much as by the operation of the holy Ghoſt, and by faith we obey the commaundements of God by Ieſus Chriſt whiche couereth with the Cloke of his
<pb facs="tcp:7035:30"/>righteouſneſſe all our wants and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs come to the third parte of our duty towards God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>We haue ſaid that it conſiſteth in an acknowledging.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What acknowledging?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Of all the benefits which we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and receiue daily at the hand of God and eſpetially of the benefit of redemption by Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Is it not for this cauſe that the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents called the holy Supper, <hi>Euchariſtia,</hi> that is to ſay, gratefulneſſe, good grace, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thanks?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It is ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Is this acknowledging neceſſary for all them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are partakers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordꝭ table?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yea. As Ieſus Chriſte hath ſhe wed vs an example,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>26.</hi> Mark. <hi>14.</hi> Luc. <hi>22. 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> and moreouer hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs to celebrate the Supper in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What are the conditions of this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>There are foure principall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Which are the two firſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt it ought tobe giuen to one onely God, by his only Sonne Ieſus Chriſte. Se condly it ought not tobe giuen not onely by
<pb facs="tcp:7035:31"/>mouth, but alſo by hart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Dooth it folowe héereby that all they which call vpon Saints &amp; giue not thanks for their ſaluation to one onely. God by his Sonne Ieſus Chriſte, are gilty?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yea. And they alſo erre which are Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrits, praying in an vnknowen tung, honouring God onely with their lips, and not with their harts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F,</speaker>
               <p>Tel me the two laſt conditions of the acknowledging.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That is, it ought to bee doon at all times, that is to ſay, aſwel in aduerſitie: as in proſperitie. To be ſhort, it ought to be practiſed not onely priuately: but alſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely, and in the middeſt of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the faithful.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing that we haue ſpoken inough of our duty towards God: let vs now ſpeak of our duty towards our neighbour,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It conſiſteth in true Charitie and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly vnitie, whiche doo neceſſarily folowe faith and the true ſeruice of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true forme &amp; rule of charity?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That we looue our neighbours as our ſelues, or that we looue one an other, euen as Chriſte looued vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>How did Chriſte looue vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>He looued vs when wee were his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes,
<pb facs="tcp:7035:31"/>and when we were wicked and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable before God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Haue we not héerein an example to looue our enemies, although they be wicked and naught?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes. For in this part we muſt be agréeable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> image of our hed, Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>And this looue wherewithall Chriſte looued vs, was it fained? or did it continue but for a time?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No, for he looued vs not in word only: but in déed. He looued vs not only for a time but euen to the end, vnto death, euen to the ſheding of his pretious blood for vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>And ought we not to folow him héerin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes. To eſchew all diſſembling &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeuer we debate of loouing our brethren and ſhewing our loue by déed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Beſide the example of Chriſte, are we not exhorted to this true looue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Super?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By what reaſons?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, in that that we doo all communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate togither at the Supper, that we eat of the ſelf ſame meate, that we call vpon one ſelf ſame Father, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue one ſelf ſame hed Ieſus Chriſte, that we are all quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his holy ſpirit, it ought to ſtir vs vp to true looue and Brotherly charitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:7035:32"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The making of the bread and wine of the Supper ought to exhort vs alſo vnto it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>How ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe that euen as the Bread is made of many cornes, which are vnite to gither in one lump of Bread, and as the Wine is made of many cluſters of grapes which are afterwarde put togither in one licour: ſo muſt the Chriſtians, whiche are many in them ſelues: be ioyned togither by looue in one ſelf ſame body, whiche is the churche of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>This looue which we are exhorted vn to by ſo many reaſons in the Supper, can it be in them whiche bere malice and batred one againſt an other?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No. And therfore we muſt forget all iniuryes and reconcile our ſelues to them which haue offended vs, and forgiue them with all our hart euen as wee would that God ſhould forgiue vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>May we conclude by all that hath béen héertofore ſpoken, that ſuch as doo not their duty aſwel towarde God as towarde their neighbour, ought not to be receyued to the Supper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, and therfore the true miniſter of Ieſus Chriſte muſt take good héed that hée
<pb facs="tcp:7035:32"/>giue not that that is holy to ſuch as are open ly knowen tobe Dogs and Swine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The father of all mercy defend vs in ſuch ſort through his holy ſpirit, with faith and repentance, that we may publiſh his praiſes with a ſincere affection, and looue our neighbours, as Ieſus Chriſte hath loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs, that we come not to his holy Table to our damnation, as Infidels and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents doo, but rather to our ſaluation, béeing aſſured that we inioy as truely eternall life with all riches and treaſures which are in Ieſus Chriſte: as we inioy the Elements whiche he appointed vs for infallible witneſſes of euerlaſting life, in the ſame his welbelooued Sonne Ieſus Chriſte our LORD.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>So be it.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Allde for Lucas Hariſon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7035:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
